<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">cyrusmaher.github.io</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2014-07-17T23:22:03-07:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Cyrus Maher</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>cyrusmaher@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fairwell academia!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/fairwell-academia/" />
  <id>/blog/fairwell-academia</id>
  <published>2014-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</published>
  <updated>2014-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cyrus Maher</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>cyrusmaher@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many bloggers have written vividly about the bittersweet process of leaving academia. The stories are strikingly similar. At a certain point, the pressure, the uncertainty, the long hours, the low-ish wages, and the endless moving from city to city simply become cumulatively unsustainable. One comes to realize that most of these circumstances do not abate if one beats the odds and lands a junior faculty position. One recognizes that, for better or for worse, this is the deal. Take it or leave it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;thinking-about-leaving&quot;&gt;Thinking about leaving&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I once overheard an undergraduate researcher ask a junior faculty member about getting into academic science. His reply was simple, “If you can imagine yourself doing anything else, go do that.” At the time I felt his advice to be overly pessimistic. Now, I have to say that I agree with him. So I’m going to go another route. Similar to Lenny Teytelman’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://anothersb.blogspot.com/2014/02/goodbye-academia.html&quot;&gt;experience leaving academia&lt;/a&gt;, “I feel liberated and happy, and this is a very bad sign for the future of life sciences in the United States.” I’ll table this last part for another day, though :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-data-behind-the-decision&quot;&gt;The data behind the decision&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see below, in 2011 there were ~35,000 new PhD graduates, but only about ~3,000 faculty openings. Academic science is overstaffed, and that is leading to unhealthy levels of competition for those who remain. Despite this persistent trend, Francis Collins has stated that he does not believe there is an oversupply of PhDs. This is partly because, even as the situation in academia is becoming increasingly dire, the “unreasonable effectiveness of data” is leading to an explosion of research positions in industries from advertising to &lt;a href=&quot;http://sciencecareers.sciencemag.org/career_magazine/previous_issues/articles/2014_06_13/science.opms.r1400143&quot;&gt;biomedicine&lt;/a&gt;. In short, we &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; needed, but mostly not in academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;http://anothersb.blogspot.com/2014/07/who-will-train-tomorrows-scientists.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ScienceOverstaffed.jpg&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; border=&quot;500&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pulling-the-trigger&quot;&gt;Pulling the trigger&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision to leave academia has been compared to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://anothersb.blogspot.com/2014/04/dear-academia-i-loved-you-but-im.html&quot;&gt;break up&lt;/a&gt;. For me, it’s been a surprisingly emotional decision, especially when I feel like I’m letting down people I care about. But at the end of the day, I’ve thought this through backwards and forwards, and I know in my bones that it’s right, so I’ve just gotta put on my big boy pants and go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My father also had a shot at becoming a professor, but he too went into industry instead. He took a job at Union Carbide, in part so that he could support my mom and older brother. During his ~30 year tenure at the company, he produced more than 40 patents. He didn’t gain much visibility from his work, but his insights were applied to globally distributed products. Today, you probably can’t go an afternoon without touching something made better or cheaper by his work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I provide this anecdote a.) because I’m proud of my dad, and b.) to make the point that there are (many) jobs in industry where you can have good career opportunities, solid pay, a high quality of life, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; make a real impact. For someone who doesn’t mind being a little picky, I honestly don’t see a downside. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;unsollicited-advice-for-graduate-students&quot;&gt;(Unsollicited) advice for graduate students&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The complexion of science has changed rapidly over the last decade. As a result, conventional wisdom often is not consistent with present circumstances. Graduate students and postdocs need to take an active role in evaluating the situation for themselves, and in demanding greater support in preparing for their most likely career outcomes. Going into industry is not failing or selling out. “Industry” isn’t even really a thing. For many, it’s a catch-all term for “that not-academia stuff I never experienced”. If you wonder what it’s like, go and look up some job postings in your area. If you find something that looks interesting, considering tailoring your training to prepare yourself for that type of job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;background-reading&quot;&gt;Background reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;personal-experiences&quot;&gt;Personal Experiences&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://m.sciencemag.org/content/345/6192/110&quot;&gt;A giant leap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bioluminate.blogspot.com/2014/02/the-seven-stages-of-grief-for-academic.html&quot;&gt;The seven stages of grief for an academic career&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://anothersb.blogspot.com/2014/03/my-life-as-phd-scientist-you-should.html&quot;&gt;My life as a PhD Scientist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;Who will train tomorrow&#39;s scientists?&quot;&gt;Who will train tomorrow’s scientists?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;a-look-at-the-system&quot;&gt;A look at the system&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pnas.org/content/111/16/5773.full&quot;&gt;Rescuing Biomedical Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.michaeleisen.org/blog/?p=1270&quot;&gt;Michael Eisen’s take on how to fix things&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/fairwell-academia/&quot;&gt;Fairwell academia!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cyrus Maher at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;cyrusmaher.github.io&lt;/a&gt; on July 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[CauseMap: Submitted to Bioinformatics!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/projects/CauseMap-Submitted/" />
  <id>/projects/CauseMap-Submitted</id>
  <published>2014-06-24T00:00:00-07:00</published>
  <updated>2014-06-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cyrus Maher</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>cyrusmaher@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve long been interested in how we can understand complex systems without dissecting out the interdependence 
that causes them to come to life. I deeply admire and value the control and certainty that a well-constructed experiment
can provide, but from the data analysis side, I think there’s much more we can do to gain a preliminary understanding of potentially interesting causal relationships. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a step in that direction, I’ve created CauseMap, an implementation of convergent cross mapping, a method developed by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://scrippsscholars.ucsd.edu/gsugihara&quot;&gt;Sugihara group&lt;/a&gt; at UCSD. The method is fairly different from what most have been exposed to, so I’ve tried to consolidate some useful explanatory resources on the project website. Check it out at &lt;a href=&quot;cyrusmaher.github.io/CauseMap.jl&quot;&gt;cyrusmaher.github.io/CauseMap.jl&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/projects/CauseMap-Submitted/&quot;&gt;CauseMap: Submitted to Bioinformatics!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cyrus Maher at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;cyrusmaher.github.io&lt;/a&gt; on June 24, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[MOSAIC: stalled by sneer review]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/projects/MOSAIC-Rejected/" />
  <id>/projects/MOSAIC-Rejected</id>
  <published>2014-05-28T00:00:00-07:00</published>
  <updated>2014-05-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cyrus Maher</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>cyrusmaher@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Problems with peer review are par for the course in academia. Not every reviewer will be evaluating work that is entirely within their area of expertise. Cranky misunderstandings about methodological issues are to be expected, but can be dealt with respectfully and even painlessly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue that we ran into with this round of review did take me aback, however. After months of waiting, our paper was rejected by Molecular Biology and Evolution based on the feedback of a &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; reviewer. What’s more, this reviewer objected to MOSAIC because he or she did not believe it was possible to integrate ortholog detection methods without degrading the quality of the end product. This is of course something we considered and addressed thorougly in the manuscript. At first when I read this critique, I thought I had perhaps concealed some of the key points of the manuscript within impenetrably drab blocks of text. Looking back, however, I found sections with titles such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The addition of new sequences does not sacrifice average levels of sequence identity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Integrating methods leads to higher levels of phylogenetic and functional concordance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These claims were supported by well-constructed figures and argumentation. Ultimately, I have trouble coming to any conclusion other than that 1.) the editor didn’t put in enough effort to find more than one reviewer, and 2.) that reviewer didn’t take the time to skim the figures or section titles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After talking to colleagues, I found out that our experience is in no way singular, which is both comforting and unsettling at the same time. I’m interested in how we can be more faithful to the basic structures that help science function properly. At the same time, I have to start thinking about how I can maximize my contribution given the current circumstance. How much freedom can academia really offer if years of work can be stymied by a single individual who did not even read your manuscript? I think that’s an important question, but for the moment I’ll table it in favor of eating a good meal and going outside :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update: After much deliberation, we decided to challenge MBE’s decision. The paper is currently under review once again…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/projects/MOSAIC-Rejected/&quot;&gt;MOSAIC: stalled by sneer review&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cyrus Maher at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;cyrusmaher.github.io&lt;/a&gt; on May 28, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[MOSAIC: Haldane's Sieve blog post is up!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/projects/HS-MOSAIC/" />
  <id>/projects/HS-MOSAIC</id>
  <published>2013-10-21T00:00:00-07:00</published>
  <updated>2013-10-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cyrus Maher</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>cyrusmaher@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;
  .centeredImage
    {
    text-align:center;
    margin-top:0px;
    margin-bottom:0px;
    padding:0px;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple weeks back, we posted the &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1309.2319&quot;&gt;manuscript&lt;/a&gt; for our new ortholog detection method, MOSAIC . Since then, we’ve had the opportunity to blog about it on Haldane’s sieve. You can read the post &lt;a href=&quot;http://haldanessieve.org/2013/10/21/author-post-a-mosaic-of-methods-improving-ortholog-detection-through-integration-of-algorithmic-diversity/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Below is a little teaser, showing that ortholog methods frequently outperform one another. This motivates the development of MOSAIC as a way to take advantage of this complementarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/PairwiseHeatMap_Blues_pluslab_neworder.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;b&gt;Comparison of sequence identity levels between methods &lt;/b&gt; A.) Heat map of the percent of orthologs for which BLAT (BL), OMA (OMA), MultiParanoid (MP), and MultiZ (MZ) outperform one another. Performance is based on percent identity of each method’s orthologs to the human sequence. One method is considered to outperform another method if it improves percent identity by at least five percentage points. Text in diagonal cells shows the number of orthologs identified by each method, colored by the percent of transcripts at which a given method outperforms all the others.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/projects/HS-MOSAIC/&quot;&gt;MOSAIC: Haldane's Sieve blog post is up!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cyrus Maher at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;cyrusmaher.github.io&lt;/a&gt; on October 21, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>
