<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">cyrusmaher.github.io</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cyrusmaher.github.io/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cyrusmaher.github.io" />
<updated>2015-09-14T07:12:03-07:00</updated>
<id>http://cyrusmaher.github.io/</id>
<author>
  <name>Cyrus Maher</name>
  <uri>http://cyrusmaher.github.io/</uri>
  <email>cyrusmaher@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sticking the landing in Biotech]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cyrusmaher.github.io/blog/sticking-landing-in-biotech/" />
  <id>http://cyrusmaher.github.io/blog/sticking-landing-in-biotech</id>
  <published>2015-06-30T00:00:00-07:00</published>
  <updated>2015-06-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cyrus Maher</name>
    <uri>http://cyrusmaher.github.io</uri>
    <email>cyrusmaher@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It has been nearly a year since I decided to forego a post-doctoral research position in favor of applying directly to jobs in biotech. I am  so happy I did!! Let me tell you why :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choosing-a-path-after-graduation&quot;&gt;Choosing a path after graduation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my PhD, I focused heavily on developing statistical, computational, and subject matter-specific skills that would 1.) allow me to meaningfully contribute to improving human health; and 2.) give me and my family a broad range of options going forward. At the end of my training, it felt like all that hard work had paid off. I had a number of enticing job offers in front of me, but one stood head and shoulders above the rest. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.humanlongevity.com/&quot;&gt;Human Longevity Inc.&lt;/a&gt; (HLI) offered me the chance to work in a vibrant, health-focused research environment, empowered by abundant and mutually reinforcing institutional resources. My job would be to work as part of a diverse team of software engineers, machine learning experts, and bioinformaticians to translate years of progress in the basic sciences into improved and extended quality of life for, say, my Mom and Dad. Oh, and we’d have more next-generation sequencing data than the rest of the world combined! I felt like I had the chance to actually help build the clinical sequencing revolution. I couldn’t pass up that opportunity. &lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.humanlongevity.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hli-logo-share_cropped.png&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; border=&quot;-20&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; hspace=&quot;0&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;looking-back-after-eight-months-on-the-job&quot;&gt;Looking back after eight months on the job&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I interviewed last Fall, HLI was just booting up and had I think 20 employees or so. There was a sense of promise and potential, but also a fair number of day-to-day headaches. We didn’t yet have our data infrastructure build, so there was a great deal of redundant grunt work to cleanse data, reconcile file formats, etc. There were also only three people in our Mountain View office when I joined, so it was also just a little too quiet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, HLI is approaching 120 employees. In the Mountain View office, we now have 15 research scientists, with two more starting on Monday. Much of our data analysis infrastructure has come together, and it’s now straightforward to run an association study on anything from cardiovascular disease to Alzheimers to aging using data from a diverse array of sources. There are still plenty of “big data” problems to work out, but that’s part of the fun! In the meantime, we’re already uncovered some publishable results that could eventually help patients. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m more excited each day about what I get to do for a living. At the same time, I’m realistic. I don’t expect my job to be some kind of intellectual paradise that can substitute for living a well-balanced life. Work almost inevitably includes plenty of frustrations and set-backs. The key thing for me is that at the end of the day, it all feels worth it. Right now, I feel like I’m devoting these years of my life to work as a valued member of a team towards projects that could prevent or heal human suffering in a lasting way. It hasn’t been all candy canes and rainbows, but the joy and fulfillment outweigh the struggle. I enjoy what I do, frustrations and all.&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;br /&gt;
p.s. If you’re interested in this kind of work, we’re hiring for both &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.humanlongevity.com/careers/open-positions/&quot;&gt;career&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.humanlongevity.com/hli-research-fellow/&quot;&gt;fellowship&lt;/a&gt; positions!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.humanlongevity.com/careers/open-positions/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/research-fellows-banner.jpg&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; border=&quot;-20&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; hspace=&quot;0&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io/blog/sticking-landing-in-biotech/&quot;&gt;Sticking the landing in Biotech&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cyrus Maher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io&quot;&gt;cyrusmaher.github.io&lt;/a&gt; on June 30, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[CauseMap: Published in PeerJ!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/CauseMap-Published/" />
  <id>http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/CauseMap-Published</id>
  <published>2015-03-05T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2015-03-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cyrus Maher</name>
    <uri>http://cyrusmaher.github.io</uri>
    <email>cyrusmaher@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s my pleasure to announce that our paper, &lt;a href=&quot;https://peerj.com/articles/824/&quot;&gt;“&lt;em&gt;CauseMap: fast inference of causality from complex time series&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/a&gt; is now available online at &lt;a href=&quot;https://peerj.com/&quot;&gt;PeerJ&lt;/a&gt;. For those who aren’t familiar with PeerJ (it’s a relatively new journal), definitely give it a look. This submission was hands-down the best publishing experience I’ve had. A couple points that were particularly refreshing: 1.) we got back responses within weeks instead of months. 2.) our reviewers provided helpful, civil feedback clearly geared toward improving the manuscript, and 3.) we were able to submit the manuscript through a sleek, modern web interface that significantly cut down the administrative overhead of the submission process. So many thanks to PeerJ for an excellent open access publishing experience :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit about the paper: we present the first open source implementation of Convergent Cross Mapping (CCM), an algorithm developed by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://scrippsscholars.ucsd.edu/gsugihara&quot;&gt;Sugihara group&lt;/a&gt; at UCSD. This is method is useful for robust causal inference from time series data. Unlike popular tools such as time-lagged regression, instrumental variables, etc.; CCM explicitly accounts for high-dimensional system dynamics encoded within time series data. In fact it’s these details that allow us to establish causality, even in the presence of confounding and interdependent non-linearity. For more details, feel free to check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://peerj.com/articles/824/&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;cyrusmaher.github.io/CauseMap.jl&quot;&gt;cyrusmaher.github.io/CauseMap.jl&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io/images/Causemap_fit.jpg&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; /&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Figure 1: An example visualization from CauseMap using abundances of Paramecium aurelia and Didinium nasutum (a predator-prey system). (A) For optimal parameter values, the convergence of the cross-map correlation with library size. (B–C). The dependence of the maximum cross-map correlation on assumed dimensionality (measured by E) and the time lag of the causal effect (measured by τp). Note that the second maximum at τp = 5 corresponds to the principal frequency of the P. aurelia and D. nasutum time series, as determined by Fourier transform analysis.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/CauseMap-Published/&quot;&gt;CauseMap: Published in PeerJ!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cyrus Maher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io&quot;&gt;cyrusmaher.github.io&lt;/a&gt; on March 05, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[MOSAIC: back and better than ever]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/MOSAIC-Reborn/" />
  <id>http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/MOSAIC-Reborn</id>
  <published>2015-02-23T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2015-02-23T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cyrus Maher</name>
    <uri>http://cyrusmaher.github.io</uri>
    <email>cyrusmaher@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/MOSAIC-Rejected/&quot;&gt;last update&lt;/a&gt;, I described the rejection of our comparative genomic method paper based on the concerns of a single reviewer. These concerns were clearly addressed both in figures and in the main text. However, we could have made the presentation clearer and more considerate to a broader audience of, e.g. interested (but potentially overworked) non-experts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I’m happy to report that that our paper has been accepted to &lt;em&gt;Genes, Genomes, and Genetics (G3)&lt;/em&gt; under the title &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.g3journal.org/content/5/4/629.long&quot;&gt;“Rock, paper, scissors: harnessing complementarity in ortholog detection methods improves comparative genomic inference.”&lt;/a&gt; They say that rejection tends to improve the quality and impact of manuscripts (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/news/rejection-improves-eventual-impact-of-manuscripts-1.11583&quot;&gt;see write-up&lt;/a&gt;). In our case, I think that the extra time and improved focus on clarity and approachability absolutely improved the presentation of the method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io/images/MOSAIC_opt.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; /&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;A schematic of MOSAIC&#39;s sequence selection algorithm. Steps: (1) Construct graph; (2) Choose the sequence from a random OD method for each species; (3) Iterate through species. For each species, pick the orthologs with highest similarity to the current best choices for all other species; (4) Return current best choices if no changes are made after iterating through all species; (5) To find global optimum, repeat steps 1-4 with random sampling paths.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit of background on the paper: comparative genomics often relies on the comparison of evolutionarily related sequences from different species (orthologs). Many methods analyze orthologous sequences, but what happens if the orthologs themselves are poorly called? In our experience, this leads to a “garbage in, garbage out” scenario. For this reason, we were motived to improve ortholog detection by building a statistical framework for harnessing the deep complementarity between methodologically diverse ortholog detection methods. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io/images/MOSAIC_MSA.jpg&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; /&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;The result of sequence integration for carbonic anhydrase 12. Orthologs that were not returned for a given species are denoted with a horizontal black bar. Those that were filtered using pre-integration sequence identity cutoffs are indicated with gray bars with the global percent identity from pairwise alignment to human included. Species name label colors denote the species of origin for orthologs in the MOSAIC alignment.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In “Paper, Rock, Scissors”, 1.) we demonstrate this methodological complementarity, 2.) we develop a tool for taking advantage of it, 3.) we show that our tool maintains or improves data quality across wide variety of measures while also retrieving a great deal more sequences, and 4.) apply our method to find an intriguing and otherwise undetectable positively selected site in TPSAB1, an enzyme linked to asthma, heart disease, and irritable bowel disease. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io/images/MOSAIC_PSS.jpg&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; /&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Example: a MOSAIC-specific PSS in Tryptase Alpha/Beta 1 (TPSAB1). The tetrameric TPSAB1 structure is shown with positively selected sites highlighted. The site detected by component methods and by MOSAIC is colored orange, whereas the MOSAIC-specific PSS is featured in red. A bound inhibitor (white) pinpoints the active site of the enzyme.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/MOSAIC-Reborn/&quot;&gt;MOSAIC: back and better than ever&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cyrus Maher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io&quot;&gt;cyrusmaher.github.io&lt;/a&gt; on February 23, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taking the leap out of academia]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cyrusmaher.github.io/blog/leap-from-academia/" />
  <id>http://cyrusmaher.github.io/blog/leap-from-academia</id>
  <published>2014-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</published>
  <updated>2014-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cyrus Maher</name>
    <uri>http://cyrusmaher.github.io</uri>
    <email>cyrusmaher@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many bloggers have written vividly about the bittersweet process of leaving academia. Yet, the stories are strikingly similar. At a certain point, the pressure, the uncertainty, the long hours, the low-ish wages, and the endless moving from city to city simply become cumulatively unsustainable. One comes to realize that most of these circumstances do not recede if one beats the odds and lands a junior faculty position. For better or for worse, this is the deal. Do you like it or not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;thinking-about-leaving&quot;&gt;Thinking about leaving&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I feel…worn down by the slow and uncertain grind through the academic ranks. I once overheard an undergraduate researcher ask a junior faculty member about getting into academic science. His reply was simple, “If you can imagine yourself doing anything else, go do that.” At the time I felt his advice to be a bit harsh. Now, I have to say that I get where he was coming from. So I’m going to go do something else. Similar to Lenny Teytelman’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://anothersb.blogspot.com/2014/02/goodbye-academia.html&quot;&gt;experience of leaving academia&lt;/a&gt;, “I feel liberated and happy, and this is a very bad sign for the future of life sciences in the United States.” Given how far this last part is from my locus of control, however, I’m focusing mostly on the “liberated and happy” part :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-data-behind-the-decision&quot;&gt;The data behind the decision&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see below, in 2011 there were ~35,000 new PhD graduates, but only about ~3,000 faculty openings. Academic science is overstaffed, and that is leading to unhealthy levels of competition for those who remain. Despite this persistent trend, Francis Collins has stated that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/naturejobs/science/articles/10.1038/nj7508-255a&quot;&gt;he does not believe there is an oversupply of PhDs&lt;/a&gt;. This is partly because, even as the situation in academia is becoming increasingly dire, the “unreasonable effectiveness of data” is leading to an explosion of research positions in industries from advertising to &lt;a href=&quot;http://sciencecareers.sciencemag.org/career_magazine/previous_issues/articles/2014_06_13/science.opms.r1400143&quot;&gt;biomedicine&lt;/a&gt;. In short, we &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; needed, but mostly not in academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;http://anothersb.blogspot.com/2014/07/who-will-train-tomorrows-scientists.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io/images/ScienceOverstaffed.jpg&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; border=&quot;500&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;making-the-leap&quot;&gt;Making the leap&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of leaving academia has been compared to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://anothersb.blogspot.com/2014/04/dear-academia-i-loved-you-but-im.html&quot;&gt;break up&lt;/a&gt;. For me, it’s been a surprisingly emotional decision, especially when people I care about seem to feel let down by my decision. But at the end of the day, I’ve thought this through backwards and forwards, and I know in my bones that it’s right. So I’ve just gotta put on my big boy pants and go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My father also had a shot at becoming a professor, but he too went into industry instead. He took a job at Union Carbide, in part so that he could support my mom and older brother. During his ~30 year tenure at the company, he produced more than 40 patents. He didn’t gain much visibility from his work, but his insights were applied to globally distributed products. Today, you probably can’t go an afternoon without touching something made better or cheaper by his work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I provide this anecdote a.) because I’m proud of my dad, and b.) to make the point that there are (many) jobs in industry where you can have good career opportunities, solid pay, a high quality of life, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; make a real impact. For someone who doesn’t mind being a little picky, I honestly don’t see a downside to taking the leap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io/images/skydive.jpg&quot; height=&quot;250&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; /&gt; 
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;In fact, sometimes leaps can be a lot of fun.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;unsollicited-advice-for-graduate-students&quot;&gt;(Unsollicited) advice for graduate students&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The staffing situation in science has changed rapidly over the last decade. As a result, conventional wisdom often is not consistent with present circumstances. Graduate students and postdocs need to take an active role in evaluating the situation for themselves, and in demanding greater support in preparing for their most likely career outcomes. Going into industry is not failing or selling out. “Industry” isn’t even really a thing. For many, it’s a catch-all term for “that not-academia stuff I never experienced”. If you wonder what it’s like, go and look up some job postings in your area of expertise. If you find something that looks interesting, considering tailoring your training to better prepare yourself for that type of job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;background-reading&quot;&gt;Background reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-selection-of-personal-experiences&quot;&gt;A selection of personal Experiences&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://m.sciencemag.org/content/345/6192/110&quot;&gt;A giant leap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most of this has been rewarding. But in the overly busy mode that most researchers operate in, I found I was feeling less
bullish about academia as I knew it and increasingly uncertain it was the right fit….
“If [impact] is my measure for success, [I thought,] “What work must I do to achieve it?” I did some deep thinking and realized that my conservation work—not my academic research—was the work that would help me achieve those lofty goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bioluminate.blogspot.com/2014/02/the-seven-stages-of-grief-for-academic.html&quot;&gt;The seven stages of grief for an academic career&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am now halfway through my 35th year and I have to admit I’m not where I thought I would be…I have come to realize that for a variety of reasons I am unlikely to achieve my lifelong goal of becoming a tenured track professor.  I am letting go of some of the… [constant] worrying about the treadmill of the next paper, the next grant, the next position…To get to this place I went through a lot of heartache and depression that closely followed the 7 stages of grief….&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://anothersb.blogspot.com/2014/03/my-life-as-phd-scientist-you-should.html&quot;&gt;My life as a PhD Scientist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am broke.  The System is broke.  And this is my story…I put the last eight years of my life on hold, and I’ve set myself up to keep it on hold for the next 5-10 years as a postdoc.  But I’m tired of this.  I want to go to the movies.  I want a dog.  I want a family.  I want to live my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;Who will train tomorrow&#39;s scientists?&quot;&gt;Who will train tomorrow’s scientists?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is the part that worries me the most. We have too many PhDs competing for postdocs. We have too many postdocs competing for fellowships and faculty positions. And we have too many professors, competing for grants. Combined, the low pay, hyper-competition, and the guaranteed uncertainty at every step make the academic track a bad career choice today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-comprehensive-list-of-quitlit&quot;&gt;A comprehensive list of “QuitLit”&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quitlit is an entire genre of blog post devoted solely to the experience of leaving academia. Find what other people have written, or contribute your own story &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AtQWPM4nERNNdHozb1lOVHZVN1p0a2pjOEtaUTVBSHc&amp;amp;usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. For convenience, you can also browse below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;embed src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/pub?key=0AtQWPM4nERNNdHozb1lOVHZVN1p0a2pjOEtaUTVBSHc&amp;amp;single=true&amp;amp;gid=0&amp;amp;output=html&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-look-at-the-system&quot;&gt;A look at the system&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pnas.org/content/111/16/5773.full&quot;&gt;Rescuing Biomedical Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.michaeleisen.org/blog/?p=1270&quot;&gt;Michael Eisen’s take on how to fix things&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/naturejobs/science/articles/10.1038/nj7508-255a&quot;&gt;PhD Overdrive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/345/6199/885.2.short&quot;&gt;Ailing academia needs culture change&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io/blog/leap-from-academia/&quot;&gt;Taking the leap out of academia&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cyrus Maher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io&quot;&gt;cyrusmaher.github.io&lt;/a&gt; on July 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[CauseMap: Submitted to Bioinformatics!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/CauseMap-Submitted/" />
  <id>http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/CauseMap-Submitted</id>
  <published>2014-06-24T00:00:00-07:00</published>
  <updated>2014-06-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cyrus Maher</name>
    <uri>http://cyrusmaher.github.io</uri>
    <email>cyrusmaher@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve long been interested in how we can understand complex systems without dissecting out the interdependence 
that causes them to come to life. I deeply admire and value the control and certainty that a well-constructed experiment
can provide, but from the data analysis side, I think there’s much more we can do to gain a preliminary understanding of potentially interesting causal relationships. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a step in that direction, I’ve created CauseMap, an implementation of convergent cross mapping, a method developed by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://scrippsscholars.ucsd.edu/gsugihara&quot;&gt;Sugihara group&lt;/a&gt; at UCSD. The method is fairly different from what most have been exposed to, so I’ve tried to consolidate some useful explanatory resources on the project website. Check it out at &lt;a href=&quot;cyrusmaher.github.io/CauseMap.jl&quot;&gt;cyrusmaher.github.io/CauseMap.jl&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/CauseMap-Submitted/&quot;&gt;CauseMap: Submitted to Bioinformatics!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cyrus Maher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io&quot;&gt;cyrusmaher.github.io&lt;/a&gt; on June 24, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[MOSAIC: stalled by sneer review]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/MOSAIC-Rejected/" />
  <id>http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/MOSAIC-Rejected</id>
  <published>2014-05-28T00:00:00-07:00</published>
  <updated>2014-05-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cyrus Maher</name>
    <uri>http://cyrusmaher.github.io</uri>
    <email>cyrusmaher@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Problems with peer review are par for the course in academia. Not every reviewer will be evaluating work that is entirely within their area of expertise. Cranky misunderstandings about methodological issues are to be expected, but can be dealt with respectfully and even painlessly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue that we ran into with this round of review did take me aback, however. After months of waiting, our paper was rejected by Molecular Biology and Evolution based on the feedback of a &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; reviewer. What’s more, this reviewer objected to MOSAIC because he or she did not believe it was possible to integrate ortholog detection methods without degrading the quality of the end product. This is of course something we considered and addressed thorougly in the manuscript. At first when I read this critique, I thought I had perhaps concealed some of the key points of the manuscript within impenetrably drab blocks of text. Looking back, however, I found sections with titles such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The addition of new sequences does not sacrifice average levels of sequence identity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Integrating methods leads to higher levels of phylogenetic and functional concordance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These claims were supported by well-constructed figures and argumentation. Ultimately, I have trouble coming to any conclusion other than that 1.) the editor didn’t put in enough effort to find more than one reviewer, and 2.) that reviewer didn’t take the time to skim the figures or section titles. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After talking to colleagues, I found out that our experience is in no way singular, which is both comforting and unsettling at the same time. I’m interested in how we can be more faithful to the basic structures that help science function properly. At the same time, I have to start thinking about how I can maximize my contribution given the current circumstance. How much freedom can academia really offer if years of work can be stymied by a single individual who did not even read your manuscript? I think that’s an important question, but for the moment I’ll table it in favor of eating a good meal and going outside :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update: After much deliberation, we decided to challenge MBE’s decision. The paper is currently under review once again…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/MOSAIC-Rejected/&quot;&gt;MOSAIC: stalled by sneer review&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cyrus Maher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io&quot;&gt;cyrusmaher.github.io&lt;/a&gt; on May 28, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[MOSAIC: Haldane's Sieve blog post is up!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/HS-MOSAIC/" />
  <id>http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/HS-MOSAIC</id>
  <published>2013-10-21T00:00:00-07:00</published>
  <updated>2013-10-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Cyrus Maher</name>
    <uri>http://cyrusmaher.github.io</uri>
    <email>cyrusmaher@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;
  .centeredImage
    {
    text-align:center;
    margin-top:0px;
    margin-bottom:0px;
    padding:0px;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple weeks back, we posted the &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1309.2319&quot;&gt;manuscript&lt;/a&gt; for our new ortholog detection method, MOSAIC . Since then, we’ve had the opportunity to blog about it on Haldane’s sieve. You can read the post &lt;a href=&quot;http://haldanessieve.org/2013/10/21/author-post-a-mosaic-of-methods-improving-ortholog-detection-through-integration-of-algorithmic-diversity/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Below is a little teaser, showing that ortholog methods frequently outperform one another. This motivates the development of MOSAIC as a way to take advantage of this complementarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io/images/PairwiseHeatMap_Blues_pluslab_neworder.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;b&gt;Comparison of sequence identity levels between methods &lt;/b&gt; A.) Heat map of the percent of orthologs for which BLAT (BL), OMA (OMA), MultiParanoid (MP), and MultiZ (MZ) outperform one another. Performance is based on percent identity of each method’s orthologs to the human sequence. One method is considered to outperform another method if it improves percent identity by at least five percentage points. Text in diagonal cells shows the number of orthologs identified by each method, colored by the percent of transcripts at which a given method outperforms all the others.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io/projects/HS-MOSAIC/&quot;&gt;MOSAIC: Haldane's Sieve blog post is up!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Cyrus Maher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://cyrusmaher.github.io&quot;&gt;cyrusmaher.github.io&lt;/a&gt; on October 21, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>
